Guide to the Ben's Chili Bowl records, 1943-2018 MS2285
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Ben's Chili Bowl records
1943-2018
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
MS2285
6 Linear Feet
This collection consists of records relating to the Washington, D.C. restaurant Ben's Chili Bowl dating from 1943-2018.
Biographical / Historical
Ben's Chili Bowl was founded on August 22, 1958, by Ben Ali, a Trinidadian-born immigrant and his fiancee, Virginia Rollins. The building they chose was that of Washington's first silent movie house, the Minnehaha. The building is a contributing property to the Greater U Street Historic District. At the time, Washington was officially segregated, and U Street was known as "Black Broadway".
The U Street corridor was devastated by the 1968 civil unrest that followed the assassination of Martin Luther King, Jr. During the civil unrest, black activist Stokely Carmichael, leader of the Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee, asked Ben to keep his restaurant open and the Alis obtained permission to stay open past curfew. The restaurant fed both the police officers and firemen working to impose order on the neighborhood, as well as the black activists.
The destruction of so many businesses led to the flight of residents towards the suburbs and the economic decline of the neighborhood through the mid-1970s to mid-1980s. The vast construction of the U Street/Cardozo Metro Station across the street from the restaurant, completed in 1991, forced still more U Street businesses to close, but Ben's Chili Bowl stayed open to feed the construction workers.
In 2008, Ben's Chili Bowl opened a second location in the newly built Nationals Park. On October 7, 2009, Ben died at the age of 82. He and his wife, Virginia, had retired from the restaurant business, having passed daily operations of Ben's Chili Bowl to their sons, Kamal and Nizam.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of the Ali family, 2010, 2014 (2010.033, 2010.043, 2014.030)
Scope and Contents
This collection contains business records, correspondence, historical documents, financial records, photographs, and clippings. The material dates from 1943-2018. These are the records of the Ali family chronicling the establishment and maintaining of the Ben's Chili Bowl restaurant.
Arrangement
Organized into 5 series: Historical records, Business records, Community outreach, Photographs, Publicity/Press
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Related
In 2020 Sonali Mirpuri donated a digital copy of her Georgetown Honors Thesis titled Mahaboob Ben Ali and His Chili Bowl: A Story of Family and Identity in the U Street Corridor
Business; Shaw (Washington, D.C.); African Americans; Washington (D.C.) -- History; Ben's Chili Bowl; Williams, Anthony; Barry, Marion; Cosby, Bill
- Historical records, 1943-2018; Series 1; 1.5 Linear Feet
  Arrangement
  Arranged chronologically
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains historical material that document the history of Ben Ali and Ben's Chili Bowl. Materials included are Ben Ali's personal documents, interviews and material from the 40th,45th and 50th Anniversaries of Ben's Chili Bowl's opening. Material dates from 1943-2018.
  - Ben's Chili Bowl history, undated; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Ben Ali's personal documents, 1943-1973; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Menus, 1960-2003; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Menus, undated; Series 1 (Box 11, Folder 4)
    General
    One menu for Ben's Chili Bowl and one menu for Next Door restaurant + bar
  - Awards, proclamations, certificates, 1986-2007; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Construction sign, 1987 (Box 10, Object 1)
  - 40th anniversary material, 1998; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 45th Anniversary material, 2003; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - 50th and 60th Anniversary material, 2008, 2018; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 50 Years of a Washington Landmark book materials, 2008; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Virginia Ali interview, 2004 February 9; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Resumes - Ali family, undated; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Radio commercial transcripts, undated; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Documentary - Welcome to Ben's, 2009; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Historical documents, 2009-2011; Series 1 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Gala events, 2010-2013; Series 1 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Virginia Ali's 80th Birthday party, 2013 December 7; Series 1 (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Banner, undated; Series 1 (Box 12, Banner 1)
    Banner reads "Ben's Chili Bowl Welcomes Ancestors of the Black Civil War Soldiers"
  - Banners, 2013; Series 1; These banners have a sticky residue on them and will require conservation work. (Box 12, Banner 3, Banner 2)
    March on Washington 50th anniversary banners
  - Ribbon and pin, undated; Series 1 (Box 12, Object 2)
    Small rolled ribbon. Advertisement stamp that reads: Reagan DCA Food and Shops. The lapel pin has scissors cutting a ribbon
  - T-shirt, 2012; Series 1 (Box 12, Object 1)
  - Poster, 2013; Series 1 (Box 12, Poster 1)
    Poster reads half smoke eating contest" H St. NE festival Ben's Chili Bowl.
  - Promotional Material, 2008-2011; Series 1 (Box SHARED 2, Folder 1)
- Business records, 1959-2014; Series 2; 1.5 Linear Feet
  This series contains material that pertain to the business operation of Ben's Chili Bowl dating from 1959-2014. Included are payroll books, correspondence, promotional designs, employee manuals, invoices and grant requests.
  - Correspondence, 1958-2007; Series 2 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 2011-2013; Series 2 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Payroll book, 1959; Series 2 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Payroll book, 1960; Series 2 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Payroll book, 1961; Series 2 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Payroll book, 1962; Series 2 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Payroll book, 1963; Series 2 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Payroll book, 1964; Series 2 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Payroll book, 1966; Series 2 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Payroll book, 1967; Series 2 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Payroll book, 1968; Series 2 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Payroll book, 1969; Series 2 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Payroll book, 1970; Series 2 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Payroll book, 1971; Series 2 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Payroll book, 1972; Series 2 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Payroll book, 1973; Series 2 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Payroll book, 1974; Series 2 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Payroll book, 1975; Series 2 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Payroll book, 1976; Series 2 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Payroll book, 1977; Series 2 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Ben's Bakery and Ice Cream material, 1991; Series 2 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Metro loan grant regquest, 1991; Series 2 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Filming for The Pelican Brief records, 1993; Series 2 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Public officials - testimonies, remarks, proclimations and flyers, 1998-2008; Series 2 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Surveillance system, 2001; Series 2 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Invoices, 2002-2008; Series 2 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Nationals Park materials, 2008; Series 2 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Spring Glen Fresh Foods agreement, 2008; Series 2 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Promotional designs, material, undated; Series 2 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Employee manuals, applications, undated; Series 2 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Planning retreat, 2014 September 7; Series 2 (Box 11, Folder 7)
- Community outreach, 1993-2011; Series 3; 1 Linear Feet
  alphabetically by project or organization, then chronologically
  This series contains material pertaining to nonprofrit work by Virginia and Nizam Ali. Included are handbooks, meeting minutes, correspondence, agendas and budgets dating from 1993-2011.
  - D.C. Civil Rights Veterans History project, 2003 March; Series 3 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Remembering U Street Festival, 1995; Series 3 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Restoration and Tourism project proposal, 2003; Series 3 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - No Murders D.C., 2001; Series 3 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - No Murders D.C., 2002; Series 3 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - No Murders D.C., 2003-2004; Series 3 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - U Street Theatre Foundation, 1988-2007; Series 3 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - U Street Theatre Foundation, 1993-1995; Series 3 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - U Street Theatre Foundation, 1994-1995; Series 3 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - U Street Theatre Foundation, 1994-1995; Series 3 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - U Street Theatre Foundation, 1995; Series 3 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - U Street historic preservation guidebooks, 2003-2008; Series 3 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - School papers written about Ben's Chili Bowl, 1996-1997; Series 3 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Documentary proposal: The Story of the Nations Capital, 1999; Series 3 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Screenplay: Breakfast at Ben's, 2003; Series 3 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Short film: U Street Blue, 2003; Series 3 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - St. Albans Lacrosse annual tournament, 2011; Series 3 (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - A View from Street Level, 2004; Series 3 (Box 5, Folder 9)
- Photographs, 1950-2010; Series 4; 1 Linear Feet
  Arranged alphabetically by subject
  This series contains the Ali family's presonal collection of photographs. Subjects covered include, the Ali family, visits by celebrities, politicians, metro construction and coverage of the 40, 45 and 50 Anniversaries.
  - Ali family, Series 4 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Authographed portraits, undated; Series 4 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Celebrities and politicians, undated; Series 4 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Celebrities and politicians, undated; Series 4 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Celebrities and politicians, undated; Series 4 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Celebrities and politicians, undated; Series 4 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Celebrities and politicians, undated; Series 4 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Celebrities and politicians, undated; Series 4 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Employees, undated; Series 4 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Employees, undated; Series 4 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Events- American Cancer Society press conference, undated; Series 4 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Events- Awards, Series 4 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Events- Bill Cosby press conference, 1985; Series 4 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Events - Bohemian Caverns, undated; Series 4 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Events- Cordoza Highschool mural painting, 2007 January 15; Series 4 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Events - Cultural Tourism D.C., 2002; Series 4 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Events- Dedication of Ben Ali Way, 1999; Series 4 (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Events- 40th anniversary, 1998; Series 4 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Events- 45th anniversary [1 of 3], Series 4 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Events- 45th anniversary [2 of 3], Series 4 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Events- 45th anniversary [3 of 3], Series 4 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Events- WPGC, 2007 August 24; Series 4 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Exterior, Series 4 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Exterior, Series 4 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Filming, Series 4 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Interior, Series 4 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Interior, Series 4 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Interior, Series 4 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Metro construction polariods, 1987-1991; Series 4 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Metro construction, 1987-1991; Series 4 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Metro construction, 1987-1991; Series 4 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Metro construction, 1987-1991; Series 4 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Nationals stadium, undated; Series 4 (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Negatives, undated; Series 4 (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Reconstruction work, 1997; Series 4 (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - Miscellaneous, undated; Series 4 (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - photographs, undated; Series 4 (Box 11, Folder 6)
- Publicity/Press, 1940-2013; Series 5; 1 Linear Feet
  This series contains material relating to press coverage of Ben's Chili Bowl. Included are an extensive collection of press clippings from 1958-2013.
  - Clippings, 1940-1950; Series 5 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Clippings, 1979-1995; Series 5 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Clippings, 1997; Series 5 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Clippings, 1998; Series 5 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Clippings, 1999; Series 5 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Clippings, 2000; Series 5 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Clippings, 2001; Series 5 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Clippings, 2002; Series 5 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Clippings, 2003; Series 5 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Clippings, 2004; Series 5 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Clippings, 2005; Series 5 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Clippings, 2006; Series 5 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Clippings, 2007; Series 5 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Clippings, 2008; Series 5 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Clippings, 2009; Series 5 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Clippings, 2009; Series 5 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Clippings, 2010; Series 5 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Clippings, undated; Series 5 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Clippings - Bill Cosby, 1985; Series 5 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Clippings - Bill Cosby, 1985; Series 5 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Clippings - web articles, 2001-2009; Series 5 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Clippings, 2007-2013; Series 5 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Publicity, 2011-2013, undated; Series 5 (Box 11, Folder 8)